One example of a technique to actually
improve the ILP of the program is three
height reduction. Let's consider a
program that looks like this. Let's say
that we need a sum of these four
registers in R8. One way to get that is
to add the first two numbers into R8 and
then add the second number and then add
the third number and then the fourth
number. However, this forms a dependence
chain because we have the dependence
here and the dependence here. So really
these instructions have to be done one
after the other. So tree height
reduction works as follows. The compiler
figures out that instead of adding one
number at a time to the sum and thus
creating a chain of dependencies, what
we can do is we can group the
computation this way. Thus getting we
first add the first two numbers and put
that in R8. Then we add the second pair
of numbers, put that in R seven. And
then we add up the R8 and R seven into
our final result R8. The dependencies
here are this and this. So now we have
two instructions that can execute in
parallel with each other because they
don't depend on each other and then a
third instruction that does depend on
them too. So if this needed three cycles
to execute, this can actually execute in
two cycles if we have a processor that
can do at least two instructions per
cycle. Three height reduction cannot
always be done. It uses associivity of
the addition operation. And you have to
keep in mind that not all operations are
associative. So we have to be careful.
We can only do this when the final
result is the same as if we did things
in the proper order. Let's say